Finding Aid for Letters, Documents, & Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- Letters, Documents, and Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
  - 1841 June 27. Thomas H. Williams ALS to Nathan Williams; Cambridge, [Massachusetts], 7 pages; Williams writes to his brother at Yale from Cambridge, where he is working and saving to attend law school soon. He transcribes Lewis J. Cist's poem, "My beautiful! My own!" Recommends newspaper articles and promises to send editions if Nathan will preserve them. Describes his recent activities, notes his financial affairs, and hopes to earn a position at the Law Library. Mentions temperance meetings, dentistry, Gives a humorous account of Harvard students setting a tool shed on fire. They produced a satirical play program entitled "Shantee Conflagration or the Baffled Sneaks," copied by Thomas. The letter also includes a scale-drawing and description of Williams' room in "Warland's Building" on Harvard Street, including placement of furniture and artwork.
  - 1841 June 28. Josiah Quincy to Mr. Wheeler; Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1 page; Note requesting Mr. Tutor Wheeler's attendance at a Harvard College faculty meeting. Possibly referring to Charles Stearns Wheeler, a tutor in Greek and History instructor from 1838-1842.
  - 1841 July 16. H[enry] H[art] Milman ALS to Dan[ie]l Webster; Westm[inste]r Abbey, [England], 4 pages; Charles and Mary Lyell will be visiting America on a scientific excursion. "Mr Lyell, you well know, is among the most distinguished Geologists in Europe." Introduces the Lyells to Webster. Milman would like to visit America to see the Niagara Falls, a primeval forest, and a vast river. "You are held in high official dignity; and I am sure as a man by sentiment and profession of peace, that the affairs of your country cannot be entrusted to those more disposed to promote public harmony between the countries, and private friendship between the individual members of either [Country?]"
  - 1841 October 17. William [Guilford] ALS to Nathan and Mrs. Guilford; Yale College, [New Haven, Connecticut], 4 pages; Imagines life at home and describes his own room. "Do you not see in that room - the floor of which is so dirty - In one corner a heap of dirty clothes and in an other a cap, four or five books and a pair of shoes?" Joined the Linonian Society. Describes his activities at Yale, including social visits, attending church services, roommates, food. See also William Guilford's letter of 1841 November 1.
  - 1841 October 22. George Peabody ALS to Messrs Peabody, Riggs & Co.; London, [England], 3 pages; Comments on financial and business matters, including loans, debts, and credits. Discusses items to be shipped on the Great Western and his limits for orders of Bank Shares. Mentions the sale of American stocks in England, Union Bank stock, an order of flour. Requests information on Samuel Taylor, formerly of George Rigg's company; send him $225 to Taylorsville, Wisconsin Territory. Money is scarce, and loans on stocks are out of the question.
  - ca. 1841 October. C. A. B. Notebook; [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania?], 21 pages; Contains remarks on Philadelphia's historic houses and landmarks (mostly quoted from John F. Watson's Annals of Philadelphia). Several newspaper articles, some illustrated, are pasted into the notebook relating to Philadelphia landmarks. Includes a number of pen-and-ink and pencil sketches, such as the monument at the Treaty Tree, a drawing of a Southwark Bank note from June 1837, and a wonderfully detailed sketch of William Penn's former residence, the "Slate-roof House," as it appeared in June 1841, signed C.A.B.. This sketch includes information on the current merchants in the house, including storefront signs and wares for sale. [The author of this journal may possibly be Charles A. Besson. A finished ink image of the "Slate Roof House" is held by the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.]
  - 1841 November 1. William [Guilford] ALS to Nathan and Mrs. Guilford; Yale College, [New Haven, Connecticut], 4 pages; Describes a violent altercation between Yale students and local firemen over a dispute about using the town Green. Notes students going to evening prayer, "some with bloody noses some with black eyes some with their arms in a sling... and some with their coats minus a tail." Discusses how the dispute continued through the night, with some students destroying a fire engine and threats of destroying a Yale building. "A Yankee is a prudent man, as long as the fight is confined to fists he is brave enough, but when it comes to attacking the rooms at night, they fear the balls of the Southerners pistols." See also William Guilford's letter of 1841 October 17.
  - 1841 November 20. C[harles] G[randison] Finney ALS to W[illia]m Dawes; Boston, [Massachusetts], 3 pages; Electing Amasa Walker as professor of Political Economy at Oberlin College. Walker has an anticonservative viewpoint and is opposed to the "Banking system & thinks this trading upon false capital a great National evil." Notes that another man seeking employment is "with us in his views in respect to plain Diet, Living, Abolition, Sanctification, &c &c." Discusses "shocking carelessness" in regards to fires in Tappan Hall. References religion in the area and gives instructions to insure his father's house.
  - 1842 February 10. Charles and Catherine Dickens ALS to J. H. Adams; Hartford, [Connecticut], 2 pages; Thank-you note for a musical performance of the previous evening.
  - 1842 February 18. T[heodore] W[illiam] Dwight ALS to Sophia N. Dwight; New Haven, [Connecticut], 3 pages; Comments on reactions to Charles Dickens, who is visiting in America. "Mr. Dickens has been all the rage here for this two weeks past. In every party, in every reading society, in every sewing circle, in every district school, in ever bar room, the cry has been ringing, where is Dickens?" Describes Dickens, noting he appears somewhat dandyish and "possesses a pardonable spice of his vanity." Mentions beards, arranging for Sophia to visit New Haven, and details of his situation there.
  - 1842 April 4. Sir Cha[rles] Lyell ALS to [Benjamin] Silliman; New York [City, New York], 3 pages; Reflection on his lectures, venues, attendees, and ticket prices. Notes poor management by the Lyceum and his expectation that he will not be fully remunerated. Anxious to do field work. Has travelled from Niagara to Georgia and met with many who "ascribe the taste they have for science to your tuition." Discusses his upcoming travel plans.
  - 1842 April 23. Geo[rge] Catlin ALS; Egyptian Hall, [London, England], 2 pages; Apologizes for delays in correspondence, attributing them to a "severe affliction." Glad for offers for assistance in Glasgow. Will be in Liverpool in the summer. Written on paper with a black border.
  - 1842 June 24. Francis Johnson Partially printed DS to E. Burd; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 1 page; Receipt for the services of Frank Johnson's band on June 22, 1842. On F. Johnson's personalized printed receipt, with an image of a music book surrounded by instruments.
  - [18]42 July 2; 1843 June 26. John C. Rives ADS and ALS to M[atthe]w St. Clair Clarke; s.l., 5 pages [total]; Two-page document concerning profits, payments, and costs associated with printing of Clarke's multi-volume work, The Documentary History of the American Revolution. Mentions [Peter] Force's printing costs. Accompanied by a three-page letter from Rives dated June 26, 1843, regarding his purchase of Clarke's interest in the work. Comments on Clarke's progress on additional volumes of the work, projected government subscriptions and appropriations, expected costs, and payments to Clarke. Includes a signed note from Clarke agreeing to the statements in the letter. [NOTE: See also Clarke's letter of March 3, 1847]
  - 1842 December 19. AL to Uncle Aaron; s.l., 2 pages; Henry did not want to let the writer see his letter, as he had misrepresented the number of people who would be present at Middletown. Has been disagreeing with Henry in regards to playing cards. Refused to return Henry's cards. "...I thought it wrong for a young man in College to have Cards for it was well to avoid the appearance of Evil." Only evidence he has that Henry uses the cards is a story he has heard of several boys, Henry included, refusing to allow a Middletown College tutor into their room. Sending the cards to Uncle Aaron.
  - 1842-1852. 3 Partially printed DsS to Samuel Tribou, 3 pages [total]; Receipts for magazine subscriptions purchased by Samuel Tribou: Youth's Companion, Boston Recorder, Illustrated Family Magazine. The receipt for the Boston Recorder has the printed date 1842 changed to 1852.
  - 1843 March 14. Philinda [Winslow] ALS to Rev. Horace Winslow; Henrietta, [New York], 4 pages; Wonders why it has been so long since he has written. Has only received one letter, "& that from the Sand[wich] Islands." Details about classes, their difficulty, etc. She mentions studying "french mental philosophy" and "conchology." She is in the process of deliberating whether or not to continue her studies. Would like to stay past the term. Her father "thinks it foolish to do so, but I am consulting my own interest." She relays information about family and friends, including Upham's plans to travel to Ohio and his education. She has been scolded for not calling on her mother. Mention of religious meetings and "unusual interest in religion in all this section of country." Presbyterians and Methodists are getting along well with each other.
  - 1843 June 22. Park Benjamin ALS to Brantz Mayer; New York, [New York], 3 pages; Regarding the style of publication for Mayer's forthcoming book. Describes "The Irish Sketch-Book" form. Notes types of paper and presses. "Moreover it will not be worked on a double-cylinder press but on an Adams press, which gives a perfect register and a beautiful impression." Mentions types of engraving plates, their effects, and limitations. Would like to use full-page wood engravings. Discusses booksellers, selling prices, and proofs. Enclosed: One-page, undated manuscript biographical sketch of Park Benjamin.
  - [18]43 August 23. J[ames] W. Watson ALS to William Young; [Princeton, New Jersey], 4 pages; Watson writes to his father that he has been continually ill, as "[c]old, very cold weather does not, and in my opinion, never can agree with me." President of Princeton advised him to stay to his rooms. However, he does not wish to return home his senior year, "the polishing year," and miss the lectures in science given by "able and efficient Professors" such as Henry and Dod. "We all know, that there is no royal road to Science, its path is obscure and rugged - its defiles many." Excuses himself for writing home so much ("you must certainly think I am troubled with a kind of epistolatory Diarrheoa..."), but since his friends left he feels as a "stranger in a strange land." Briefly comments on finances.
  - 1843 November 13. Emma Willard ALS to Miss English; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 2 pages; Letter of introduction for Mr. Nichols, an agent for the publishers of her "historical works." Reflects on her recent divorce and its impact on "the estimation of many who loved me. But bad as that was, to have violated my own conscience and lost 'the peace of God' in my heart, would have been worse." Notes general drop in school enrollment because of hard times.
  - 1843 December. J. M. Cleaveland ALS to Henry W. Cleaveland; Princeton, [New Jersey], 2 pages; Cleaveland gives a fanciful depiction of the terrors of the night, student's late-night studying, and alcohol abuse during "revels with the jolly crew." Assures his family that he has taken the teetotal pledge, and wrote the "above nonsense... more for sport and to let off steam than anything."
  - 1844 January 11. William A. Rogers ALS to John W. Andrews; Springfield, [Ohio], 3 pages; Suspects that Andrews' assertion of a link between poverty and population levels is true. "I suppose the increase of poverty and population to spring in those cases from the same cause - a preponderance of the animal passions over the moral sentiments - of a love of present indulgence over a provident regard for the future welfare of the individual and his family..." Compares Irish and Scottish residents to illustrate his point. Worries about the availability of land and the spread of disease and famine if the American population continues to grow.
  - 1844 January 24. Jospeh Noyes ALS to Noah J. Noyes; Boston, [Massachusetts], 3 pages; Tells of his son, George, being shipwrecked in the Pacific Ocean on a deserted island for seven months. "4 of the crew were drown'd, the rest about 24 in all made a raft & got clear from the rocks & moor'd in 2 fathoms water & were obliged to ride out 8 days & 7 nights... then they got on shore, But no hou[s]es or tree all desolate without man, or beast except a Dog." Eventually rescued and taken to the Sandwich Islands, and George took a position with a merchant in Oahu. His daughter settled in Cincinnati, [Ohio]. Has suffered financial losses and is sending notes in the hopes that Noah can help him settle some outstanding bills he needs to collect. Post-script details a falling out with a Mr. Coombs over a debt. See also: Joseph Noyes ALS to Noah J. Noyes, February 9, 1846.
  - 1844 April 14. Samuel Orcutt ALS to Joseph W. Wright; Owego, [New York], 3 pages; Describes their move to Owego, the region, its agriculture, lumbering business, and residents. Father considering buying a farm. "...the people seem to be verry kind, and kind the right way too, there are some I expect that would like to pick a fellow's pocket, but they seem in general to be verry obliging to us as strangers." Notes religion and education in the area. Experiencing emotional pangs upon moving away from friends and family.
  - 1844 August 22. M[atthew] Brown ALS; Canonsburg, [Pennsylvania], 2 pages; Will be resigning his position, likely as President of Jefferson College, at the next board meeting and hopes a successor will be appointed, possibly the recipient. Assurance of the successor's acceptance of the position will limit disruption and harm to the college. Mentions an upcoming meeting of the Presbyterian Synod. Notes some calling for Robert Brackenridge, Professor Green, and Mr. Guffey to be his successor.
  - [before 1844 December 25]. Samuel McDowell DS; AMs, 6 pages [total]; Commissioners appointed to "select a scite to build a county Jail" chose to use the "present jail lot." Appoint E. P. McNeal, Austin Miller, and E. C. Crisp as jail commissioner to "superintend the erection" of the jail and make necessary contracts to complete the jail by 25 December 1844. Signed by Samuel McDowell, clerk. Includes architectural plans for the county jail.
  - 1844 December 26. J[ames] Montgomery ALS to [Fanny Bury] Palliser; Sheffield, [England], 3 pages; Poet Montgomery gives Mrs. Palliser permission to use some of his pieces in the poetry collection she is publishing, but warns her "that it will be well for you to secure yourself from loss,... verse, original or selected, being the least marketable of all literacy commodities." He amusingly describes the letters he receives from hopeful poets "as a notorious character in the way of literature," and the burden it is for him to be unable to help them. Likely written to Fanny Bury Palliser about her collection, Modern Poetical Speaker (London: 1845).
  - [between 1844 and 1851]. Laura Bridgman ALS to [George Nixon] Briggs; [Boston, Massachusetts], 1 page; Letter written to Massachusetts Representative George Nixon Briggs, governor of Massachusetts from 1844-1851, from Laura Brigman, the first known deaf/blind person to be educated. The letter offers kind words and hopes that Briggs will come and visit the Perkins Institution again to see her and the rest of "the blind girls" again. She also mentions sending Julia Brace, who was a student at the institution for a year, a present.
  - 1845 February 4. J[ames] Fenimore Cooper ALS to Jos[eph] R[eed] Ingersoll; Cooperstown, [New York], 1 page; Comments on "how near you and I are to making a Marquess" and encourages him to proceed. References the "Bloody Lord John." Acknowledges that he owes Ingersoll some money. "We need not muster all the Johnstone's in the books, but stick to the noble line." Curious about the genealogy of Thomas Gregory and Patrick Henry. Offended Campbell by refusing to go with him on a social visit. Mentions transatlantic postage. Original in [To Be] Goldstar.
  - 1845 February 4. W[illia]m A[ugustus] Sackett ALS to John H. Sackett; Seneca Falls, [New York], 3 pages; Comments on the value of education and urges him not to stop his classical studies. Remarks on the usefulness of knowing ancient languages. "You say Washington did not understand these languages This may be true- but he lived in a different period & acquired his distinction by different means." Gov. [Williah H.] Seward (1801-1872) was at John Sackett's family home. Jests about "Yankee girls" and whether they can "understand the Catechism & can make pumpkin pies in a way about to the liking of us Yorkers." Sends regards to Mr. and Mrs. Crittenden. Remarks on the election of Trustees to the Academy, including himself, and the possible removal of the male teacher. Expects their factory to be operational soon.
  - 1845 February 28. [Nicholas Marie] Alexandre Vattemare ALS to [Philip C. Johnson or William B. Hartwell]; Paris, [France], 6 pages [total]; Received the five boxes of "splendid collections of Books, maps, Minerals &c" to be distributed to libraries. Pleased with how this reflects on the people of Maine. The Museum of Natural History and the Royal School of Mines are preparing "collections of Mineralogical and Geological specimens" to send to Maine. Comments on details of arranging future international exchanges of biological and geological specimens. Requests additional copies of maps for the Secretary of the Navy, Secretary of War, and Geographical Library. Includes a "List of Books transmitted to the Honorable Secretary of the State of Maine for the State Library."
  - 1845 March 19. Uriel Farmin ALS to Noah and Samuel Jewett; Ceresco, Wisconsin Territory, 3 pages; Regarding the principles of Fourierism. Comments on the evils of the "Isolated household, and the unitary mode of doing business," noting nature's tendency to form groups and associations. "See cattle and Horses in their natural state go in herds. Yea and men in their wild state, do the same. Look at our Western savages. Look at the Turk and the wandering Moor." Believes the divine injunction to "Love thy neighbor as yourself" requires communal living. Discusses the working man's plight under capitalism, especially in European cities and in mines. "His case is immensely worse than the slavery of the Africans of the South.—The master of the negro slave is bound by law to keep his slave and provide for his wants, in sickness and old age. But the poor man who has to labor for his bread, barely enough many times to sustain life." Argues that capitalism and individualism inspire crime and allow for the rise of "peace officers, such as Lawyers, Judges, Justices, Pettifog[g]ers &c—a complete set of Blood Suckers, Idlers, non-producers, living upon the labor, the bone, and the sinew of the nation." Advocates for the need to unify interests. Discusses communal property, arbitration without lawyers, and the underlying beliefs of Associationism.
  - 1845 April 9. Albert Barnes ALS to A[ndrew] H[ull] Foot[e]; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 3 pages; Thanks Foote for the gift of a cane from overseas, "that sacred mountain." Notes recent "remarkable coldness and deadness in religion," with few revivals. Discusses people from "the asylum." Mentions the recent publication by the U.S. Exploring Expedition.
  - 1845 May 11. Joseph G. Cormick ALS to Isaac Fowler; [Columbus, Ohio], 2 pages; Letter from the Ohio State Penitentiary to the Sheriff of Sandusky, offering a description of a 15-year-old escaped prisoner, William H. Green. Notes his known travels, physical appearance, and clothing.
  - 1845 July 16. T[imothy] S[hay] Arthur ALS to Amelia B. Welby; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 1 page; Is editing a handsome annual and requests a contribution of a poem.
  - 1845 September 30. Benjamin P[erley] Poore ALS; Paris, [France], 2 pages; Trying to determine which of the papers he mailed have been mislaid. Remarks on the historical research he has undertaken for the recipient. Looked at accounts of "Radisson's expedition to Hudson's Bay," especially materials relating to La Salle. Copied a document from 1632 relating to the "restoration of Quebec," Samuel de Champlain, and Jacques Cartier. Believes the American continent was discovered by Cousin in 1488, and provides some notes on Cousin's travels. Is busy "accumulating a large quantity of matter for the State." The Parisian Legation is uninterested in his work. Has access to Marine and War Departments, but expects Mr. Broadhead's recent report may restrict future use. Attempting to access other archives.
  - 1845 October 16. AL to Tim C. Ward; New Albany, [Indiana], 7 pages; Happy to have heard from home, Fryeburg, Maine, but expresses homesickness. Will stay in New Albany for another term, even though it is difficult to retain students due to the summer break and the "Hoosier love of change." A school for girls which has recently opened and the nearby Anderson school have drawn away students. Has had to stay in New Albany due to debts he has incurred while not being paid. Does not believe "any school in this western country can flourish be profitable and live long-- that hasn't money to hold it up it won't live on its reputation as many of our eastern schools do." Notes the high number of charity students, the burden of unpaid tuition, and the unlikelihood of their school's survival. Will keep trying to make a living in the West, believing his options better than back east. Considering moving to Tennessee, believing teachers do better when they move frequently. Advises them not to emigrate to the West. Brief mention of a daguerreotype artist.
  - 1845 December 25. C. S. Keeler ALS to Henry [C. Nash]; [Whitestown, New York?], 5 pages; Declined invitation to sleigh ride because of poor health and low spirits. Mentions Christmas and working in a store. Comments on Thanksgiving and feeling poorly about not celebrating holidays. Finds tending the store difficult work and has contemplated quitting. Talks of visiting Pittsfield, [Massachusetts], old acquaintances there, and members of the Pittsfield Young Ladies Institute. Feeling lonesome after selling his canary. Reminiscences about school friends, sleighing and skating, including a story about an African American falling into a pond, correcting himself after using a racial epithet.
  - [1845]. Signature; s.l., 1 page; Ojibwa totem, "Moonlight Night." "Flying Gull" crossed out. Possibly the autograph of Gish-ee-gosh-e-gee, whose portrait was painted by George Catlin in 1845.